Well, we all need a reason to wake up.
حسنا، جميعا نحتاجُ سببا للاستيقاظ.
For me, it just took 11,000 volts.
بالنسبة لي , أحتاج الأمر إلى 11,000 فولت
I know you're too polite to ask,
أعلم بأنكم خجولين لتسئلوا
so I will tell you.
لذا سأخبركم
One night, sophomore year of college,
في ليلة ما , السنة الثانية في الكلية
just back from Thanksgiving holiday,
عائداً من عطلة عيد الشكر
a few of my friends and I were horsing around,
بعض أصدقائي وأنا كنا نتسكع بالجوار
and we decided to climb atop a parked commuter train.
وقررنا أن نصعد على سقف قطار متوقف
It was just sitting there, with the wires that run overhead.
كان هناك . وبالأسلاك التي تتحرك أعلاه
Somehow, that seemed like a great idea at the time.
بطريقة ما , بدت تلك فكرة رائعة في تلك اللحظة
We'd certainly done stupider things.
لقد فعلنا إشياء أكثر غباءاً
I scurried up the ladder on the back,
هرولت صاعداً على السلم في الخلف
and when I stood up,
وعندما وقفت
the electrical current entered my arm,
دخل التيار الكهربائي إلى ذراعي
blew down and out my feet, and that was that.
أسفل وخارج قدمي , هذا كل مافي الأمر
Would you believe that watch still works?
هل تصدقون بأن تلك الساعة مازالت تعمل
Takes a licking!
تتحمل الصدمات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My father wears it now in solidarity.
والدي يرتديها كنوع من التضامن
That night began my formal relationship with death -- my death --
تلك الليلة بدأت علاقتي الرسمية مع الموت -- موتي--
and it also began my long run as a patient.
وإيضاً بدأ مشواري الطويل كمريض
It's a good word.
أنها كلمة جيدة
It means one who suffers.
تعني الشخص الذي يعاني
So I guess we're all patients.
لذا أعتقد بأننا كلنا مرضى
Now, the American health care system
الآن ,نظام الرعاية الصحية الأمريكي
has more than its fair share of dysfunction --
لديه نصيبه العادل من الأختلال الوظيفي
to match its brilliance, to be sure.
ليناسب تألقه , لتكون متأكداً
I'm a physician now, a hospice and palliative medicine doc,
أنا طبيب الآن,طبيب نُزل ورعاية تلطيفية
so I've seen care from both sides.
لذا فلقد شهدت الرعاية من الجانبين
And believe me: almost everyone who goes into healthcare
وصدقوني, كل شخص يلتحق بالنظام الصحي
really means well -- I mean, truly.
يقصد خيراً -- أعني , بحق
But we who work in it are also unwitting agents
لكن نحن من نعمل فيه, نحن إيضا وكلاء من غير قصد
for a system that too often does not serve.
لنظام لايخدم بالعادة
Why?
لماذا؟
Well, there's actually a pretty easy answer to that question,
حسناً,هنالك إجابة جداً سهلة لهذا السؤال,
and it explains a lot:
وتوضح الكثير
because healthcare was designed with diseases, not people, at its center.
لأن نظام الرعاية الصحية كان مصمماً للأمراض لا للأشخاص, في أساسه
Which is to say, of course, it was badly designed.
ما يعني ,بالطبع , أنه مصمم بشكل سيء
And nowhere are the effects of bad design more heartbreaking
لامجال لتأثيرات التصميم السيء أن تكون أكثر مأساوية
or the opportunity for good design more compelling
أو الفرصة للتصميم الجيد أن تكون أكثر إلزاماً
than at the end of life,
من نهاية الحياة
where things are so distilled and concentrated.
حيث الأشياء جداً مرشحة ومركزة
There are no do-overs.
لامجال للمحاولة من جديد
My purpose today is to reach out across disciplines
غايتي اليوم هي أن أتواصل مع كل المجالات
and invite design thinking into this big conversation.
وأن ادعو التفكير التصميمي إلى هذا الحوار الكبير
That is, to bring intention and creativity
هذا , لجلب الهمة والإبداع
to the experience of dying.
لتجربة الموت
We have a monumental opportunity in front of us,
لدينا هذه الفرصة العظيمة أمامنا
before one of the few universal issues
أمام واحدة من القضايا العالمية القليلة
as individuals as well as a civil society:
كفرد أيضاُ وكمجتمع مدني
to rethink and redesign how it is we die.
لنعيد التفكير و التصميم لكيف سنموت
So let's begin at the end.
لذا دعونا نبدأ من النهاية
For most people, the scariest thing about death isn't being dead,
لمعظم الناس , أكثر أمر أخافة في الموت ليس أن يكونوا ميتين
it's dying, suffering.
إنما الأحتضار , المعاناة
It's a key distinction.
إنه الفارق الرئيسي
To get underneath this, it can be very helpful
لنتفهم الأمر أكثر سيكون مفيد جداً
to tease out suffering which is necessary as it is,
أن نستخرج المعاناة الضرورية في أساسها
from suffering we can change.
من المعاناة التي نستطيع تغييرها
The former is a natural, essential part of life, part of the deal,
النوع الأول طبيعي , جزء أساسي للحياة , جزء من الصفقة
and to this we are called to make space, adjust, grow.
ولهذا نحن نُدعى لأن نصنع حيز تكيف, نضج
It can be really good to realize forces larger than ourselves.
من الجيد أن نعي أن هناك قوى أعظم منا
They bring proportionality,
يجلبون التناسب
like a cosmic right-sizing.
كتصحيح كوني
After my limbs were gone,
بعد خسارة أطرافي
that loss, for example, became fact, fixed --
هذه الخسارة, على سبيل المثال أصبحت حقيقة ثابتة
necessarily part of my life,
بشكل ضروري جزء من حياتي
and I learned that I could no more reject this fact than reject myself.
وتعلمت بأنني لاأستطيع أن أرفض هذه الحقيقة أن أرفض نفسي
It took me a while, but I learned it eventually.
أستغرق الأمر مني وقتاً لكن تعلمته بالنهاية
Now, another great thing about necessary suffering
الآن , أمر عظيم آخر عن المعاناة الضرورية
is that it is the very thing
أنه هو الشيء الحقيقي
that unites caregiver and care receiver --
الذي يوحد مقدم الرعاية ومستقبل الرعاية
human beings.
البشر.
This, we are finally realizing, is where healing happens.
أخيرا ,بدأنا نستوعب إين يبدأ التعافي
Yes, compassion -- literally, as we learned yesterday --
نعم , الشفقة -- تماماً كما تعلمنا بالأمس
suffering together.
أن نعاني سويةً
Now, on the systems side, on the other hand,
الآن ,من جهة النظام,من ناحية أخرى
so much of the suffering is unnecessary, invented.
الكثير من المعاناة غير ضرورية, مُبتدعة
It serves no good purpose.
لاتخدم غاية جيدة
But the good news is, since this brand of suffering is made up,
لكن الخبر الجيد, في حين أن هذا النوع من المعاناة مُختلق
well, we can change it.
حسناً, بإستطاعتنا تغييره
How we die is indeed something we can affect.
كيف نموت أمر بكل تأكيد نستطيع التأثير فيه
Making the system sensitive to this fundamental distinction
أن نجعل النظام حساس لهذا الإختلال الأساسي
between necessary and unnecessary suffering
بين الألم والألم الغير ضروري
gives us our first of three design cues for the day.
يعطينا أول ثلاثة تلميحات تصميميه لهذا اليوم
After all, our role as caregivers, as people who care,
بعد كل شي, دورنا كمقدمين الرعاية. كأناس يكترثون
is to relieve suffering -- not add to the pile.
هو أن نخفف الألم, لا أن نزيد الأمر سوءاً
True to the tenets of palliative care,
طبقاً لمبادئ الرعاية التلطيفية,
I function as something of a reflective advocate,
أنا أعمل كداعي للتأمل
as much as prescribing physician.
بالضبط كما أنا طبيب واصف للدواء
Quick aside: palliative care -- a very important field but poorly understood --
ملحوظة جانبية , الرعاية التلطيفية -- هو مجال مهم لكن يُساء فهمه
while it includes, it is not limited to end of life care.
في حين أنه يحوي,ليس محصورا على رعاية نهاية الحياة
It is not limited to hospice.
ليس محصورا لدور الرعاية
It's simply about comfort and living well at any stage.
ببساطة هو حول الراحة وأن تعيش جيداً في أي مرحلة
So please know that you don't have to be dying anytime soon
أرجوكم أعلموا أنه ليس عليك أن تموت قريباً
to benefit from palliative care.
حتى تستفيد من الرعاية التلطيفية
Now, let me introduce you to Frank.
الآن, دعوني أعرفكم على فرانك
Sort of makes this point.
لتوضيح هذه النقطة
I've been seeing Frank now for years.
أنا أتابع مع فرانك لسنوات حتى الآن
He's living with advancing prostate cancer on top of long-standing HIV.
هو يعيش مع سرطان البروستات المتقدم إضافة إلى فيروس العوز المناعي البشري
We work on his bone pain and his fatigue,
نعمل على ألم عظامه واعيائه
but most of the time we spend thinking out loud together about his life --
لكن نقضي أكثر الوقت نفكر بصوت عالي سوية حول حياته
really, about our lives.
حقاً, عن حياتنا
In this way, Frank grieves.
بهذه الطريقة, فرانك يتعامل مع حزنه
In this way, he keeps up with his losses as they roll in,
بهذه الطريقة , هو يواكب خسارته عندما تصل إليه
so that he's ready to take in the next moment.
حتى يكون جاهزاً ليحتمل اللحظة المقبلة
Loss is one thing, but regret, quite another.
الخسارة شيء , لكن الندم أمر آخر تماماُ
Frank has always been an adventurer --
فرانك لطالما كان مغامراً
he looks like something out of a Norman Rockwell painting --
يبدو كأنه من لوحات نورمان روكويل
and no fan of regret.
ولايحب الندم
So it wasn't surprising when he came into clinic one day,
لذا لم يكن الأمر مفاجئاً لما جاء إلى العيادة في يوم
saying he wanted to raft down the Colorado River.
قائلاُ أنه يريد أن يطوف بالقارب نهر كولورادو
Was this a good idea?
هل كانت فكرة جيدة ؟
With all the risks to his safety and his health, some would say no.
مع كل المخاطر لسلامته ولصحته , البعض سيقول لا
Many did, but he went for it, while he still could.
الكثير قالوا, لكنه فعلها, في حين أنه لايزال بإمكانه
It was a glorious, marvelous trip:
كانت رحلةً جميلة ورائعة
freezing water, blistering dry heat, scorpions, snakes,
مياه متجمدة ,طقس حار جاف عقارب , أفاعي
wildlife howling off the flaming walls of the Grand Canyon --
حياة برية تعوي من خلال جدران غراند كانيون
all the glorious side of the world beyond our control.
كل الجانب البهي لهذا العالم خارج سيطرتنا
Frank's decision, while maybe dramatic,
قرار فرانك ,في حين أنه مفاجئ
is exactly the kind so many of us would make,
هو بالضبط نفس القرار الذي سيتخذه معظمنا
if we only had the support to figure out what is best for ourselves over time.
لو أن لدينا الدعم لنستنتج ماهو الأفضل لنا مع مرور الوقت
So much of what we're talking about today is a shift in perspective.
الكثير مما نتحدث عنه اليوم هو تحول في المنظور
After my accident, when I went back to college,
بعد حادثتي, لما عدت إلى الجامعة
I changed my major to art history.
غيرت تخصصي إلى تاريخ الفن
Studying visual art, I figured I'd learn something about how to see --
دراسة الفنون المرئية,أقتنعت أن أتعلم كيف أرى
a really potent lesson for a kid who couldn't change
درس قوي لفتى لم يكن يستطيع التغيير
so much of what he was seeing.
كثيراً فيما كان يراه
Perspective, that kind of alchemy we humans get to play with,
المنظور, هذا النوع من الكيمياء نحن البشر نستطيع أن نلعب فيها
turning anguish into a flower.
أن نحول العذاب إلى وردة
Flash forward: now I work at an amazing place in San Francisco
إلى الأمام , انا الآن أعمل في مكان رائع في سان فرانسيسكو
called the Zen Hospice Project,
يدعى "زن هوسبس بروجكت"
where we have a little ritual that helps with this shift in perspective.
حيث لدينا بعض الطقوس التي تساعد في تغيير المنظور
When one of our residents dies,
حين يموت أحد النزلاء
the mortuary men come, and as we're wheeling the body out through the garden,
رجال الدفن يأتوا وفي حين ندفع الجثة مروراً بالحديقة
heading for the gate, we pause.
متجهين للبوابة , نتوقف
Anyone who wants --
أي شخص يرغب
fellow residents, family, nurses, volunteers,
أحد النزلاء الآخرين, العائلة, الممرضين المتطوعين
the hearse drivers too, now --
وحتى قائدي عربة الموتى
shares a story or a song or silence,
يشاركون بقصة أو أغنية أو بالصمت
as we sprinkle the body with flower petals.
في حين ننثر الجثة ببتلات الورد
It takes a few minutes;
يأخد الأمر بضع دقائق
it's a sweet, simple parting image to usher in grief with warmth,
جميل, صورة فراق بسيطة لنستهل الحزن بحميمية
rather than repugnance.
بدلاً من المقت والنفور
Contrast that with the typical experience in the hospital setting,
على النقيض من هذا التجربة التقليدية في المستشفيات
much like this -- floodlit room lined with tubes and beeping machines
تماماً هكذا- غرفة مضيئة وأنابيب والآت تصدر صفيراً
and blinking lights that don't stop even when the patient's life has.
وأضواء تومض لاتتوقف حتى لو حياة المريض توقفت
Cleaning crew swoops in, the body's whisked away,
طاقم التنظيف يدخل ,والجثة تقاد بعيداً
and it all feels as though that person had never really existed.
وكل شيء يبدو وكأنما ذلك الشخص لم يكن
Well-intended, of course, in the name of sterility,
بحسن نية بالطبع ,بأسم قلة الحيلة
but hospitals tend to assault our senses,
لكن المستشفيات تعمد لأن تهين إدراكنا
and the most we might hope for within those walls is numbness --
وأعظم مانطمح له داخل تلك الجدران هو التخدر
anesthetic, literally the opposite of aesthetic.
مخدر فعلياً هو عكس للجمالي
I revere hospitals for what they can do; I am alive because of them.
أنا أقُدر ماتفعله المستشفيات فاأنا حي بسببهم
But we ask too much of our hospitals.
لكننا نطالب بالكثير من مستشفياتنا
They are places for acute trauma and treatable illness.
هي أماكن للأمراض البدنية الحادة والأمراض القابلة للعلاج
They are no place to live and die; that's not what they were designed for.
لايوجد مكان حيث تعيش وتموت ليس لهذا الأمر صممت
Now mind you -- I am not giving up on the notion
تذكروا, أنا لا أتخلى عن فكرة
that our institutions can become more humane.
أن تكون مؤسساتنا أكثر إنسانية
Beauty can be found anywhere.
تستطيع إيجاد الجمال في أي مكان
I spent a few months in a burn unit
قضيت بضعة اشهر في وحدة الحروق
at St. Barnabas Hospital in Livingston, New Jersey,
في مستشفى القديس برنابا في ليفينق , نيوجرسي
where I got really great care at every turn,
حيث تلقيت رعاية عظيمة من كل ناحية
including good palliative care for my pain.
متضمنة رعاية تلطيفية عظيمة لألمي
And one night, it began to snow outside.
في أحدى الليالي , بدأ الثلج بالنزول بالخارج
I remember my nurses complaining about driving through it.
أتذكر ممرضاتي يشتكين من القيادة خلاله
And there was no window in my room,
ولم يكن هناك شباك في غرفتي
but it was great to just imagine it coming down all sticky.
لكن كان عظيماً أن أتخيله يتساقط وكله لزج
Next day, one of my nurses smuggled in a snowball for me.
اليوم التالي ,واحدة من ممرضاتي هربت كرة ثلج لي
She brought it in to the unit.
أحضرتها إلى الوحدة
I cannot tell you the rapture I felt holding that in my hand,
لاأستطيع أن أخبركم عن البهجة التي شعرتها حاملاً إياها في يدي
and the coldness dripping onto my burning skin;
والبرودة تقطر على جلدي المحترق
the miracle of it all,
والمعجزة الأكبر
the fascination as I watched it melt and turn into water.
السحر وأنا أشاهدها تذوب وتتحول إلى ماء
In that moment,
في تلك اللحظة
just being any part of this planet in this universe mattered more to me
أن أكون جزء من هذا الكوكب في هذا الكون كان أهم لدي
than whether I lived or died.
من مجرد أن أحيا أو أموت
That little snowball packed all the inspiration I needed
تلك الكرة الثلجية الصغيرة اعطتني كل الألهام الذي أحتجته
to both try to live and be OK if I did not.
لأن أحاول أن اعيش وأن أكون بخير أن لم أكن
In a hospital, that's a stolen moment.
في المستشفى , تلك اللحظة الجميلة
In my work over the years, I've known many people
في عملي وعلى مر السنين , تعرفت على الكثيرين
who were ready to go, ready to die.
ممن كانوا مستعدين للمغادرة مستعدين للموت
Not because they had found some final peace or transcendence,
ليس لأنهم وجدوا السلام أو السمو
but because they were so repulsed by what their lives had become --
لكن لأنهم مهزومين مما أصبحت عليه حياتهم
in a word, cut off, or ugly.
في كلمة ,معزولة أو بشعة
There are already record numbers of us living with chronic and terminal illness,
هنالك أرقام مسجلة لحالات تعيش مع أمراض مزمنة وعضال
and into ever older age.
حتى عمر متقدم
And we are nowhere near ready or prepared for this silver tsunami.
ومحالة أن نكون جاهزين أو حتى مستعدين لهذا التسونامي الفضي
We need an infrastructure dynamic enough to handle
نحن بحاجة إلى بنية تحتيه حيوية تكفي للتعامل مع
these seismic shifts in our population.
هذه التحولات الزلزالية في عدد السكان
Now is the time to create something new, something vital.
حان الوقت لإنشاء شيء ما جديد شيء حيوي
I know we can because we have to.
أعلم أنه يمكننا لأن يجب علينا
The alternative is just unacceptable.
البديل لم يعد كافياً
And the key ingredients are known:
والمكونات الرئيسية معروفة :
policy, education and training,
السياسة , التعليم والتدريب
systems, bricks and mortar.
النظام , الطوب والمِلاط.
We have tons of input for designers of all stripes to work with.
لدينا الكثير من المدخلات لمصممين من جميع الشرائح للعمل معها
We know, for example, from research
تعلمون, على سبيل المثال, من الأبحاث
what's most important to people who are closer to death:
ماهو الشيء المهم للأشخاص القريبين من الموت
comfort; feeling unburdened and unburdening to those they love;
الراحة ,الشعور بأنهم محررين وليسوا حِملاً على من يحبون
existential peace; and a sense of wonderment and spirituality.
سلام وجودي , والشعور بالروعة والروحانية
Over Zen Hospice's nearly 30 years,
في دار الرعاية "زن هوسبس " لقرابة 30 عام
we've learned much more from our residents in subtle detail.
تعلمنا الكثير من نزلاءنا حتى أدق التفاصيل
Little things aren't so little.
الاشياء الصغيرة ليست جداً صغيرة
Take Janette.
لنتحدث عن جانيت
She finds it harder to breathe one day to the next due to ALS.
كل يوم تجد صعوبة في التنفس بسبب التصلب الجانبي الضموري
Well, guess what?
حسناً, احزروا ماذا ؟
She wants to start smoking again --
لقد قررت أن تبدأ التدخين مجدداً
and French cigarettes, if you please.
وسجائر فرنسية, لو سمحت
Not out of some self-destructive bent,
ليس من مبدأ التدمير الذاتي,
but to feel her lungs filled while she has them.
لكن حتى تشعر بأن رئتيها قد أمتلئت في حين أنها لازالت تملكهم
Priorities change.
الأولويات تتغير.
Or Kate -- she just wants to know
أو كيت -- فقط أرادت أن تعرف
her dog Austin is lying at the foot of her bed,
أن كلبها (أوستن) مازال نائماً عند قدميها على السرير
his cold muzzle against her dry skin,
أنفه البارد يلامس جلدها الجاف
instead of more chemotherapy coursing through her veins --
بدلا من المزيد من العلاج الكيميائي يتعقب أوردتها
she's done that.
لقد فعلت هذا.
Sensuous, aesthetic gratification, where in a moment, in an instant,
الإشباع الحسي والجمالي حين يكون في برهة في لحظة
we are rewarded for just being.
نشعر بأننا نكافئ فقط لوجودنا
So much of it comes down to loving our time by way of the senses,
الكثير منه يأتي من حبنا لوقتنا عن طريق الحواس
by way of the body -- the very thing doing the living and the dying.
عن طريق الجسد ,الشيء الأكيد أننا نعيش ونموت
Probably the most poignant room
لربما أكثر غرفة مؤثرة
in the Zen Hospice guest house is our kitchen,
في بيت الضيوف في "زن هوسبس" أنها المطبخ
which is a little strange when you realize
الغريب بالأمر حين تكتشف
that so many of our residents can eat very little, if anything at all.
أن الكثير من نزلائنا يأكلون القليل, أو لاشيء على الأطلاق
But we realize we are providing sustenance on several levels:
لكن أكتشفنا أننا نقدم القوت على عدة مستويات:
smell, a symbolic plane.
الرائحة,طائرة رمزية.
Seriously, with all the heavy-duty stuff happening under our roof,
بحق , حتى في حين حدوث الامور الثقيلة تحت سقفنا
one of the most tried and true interventions we know of,
واحدة من أكثر التدخلات المجربة والحقيقة التي عرفنا بها,
is to bake cookies.
هي خبز البسكويت
As long as we have our senses --
لطالما نملك حواسنا--
even just one --
لو حتى واحدة
we have at least the possibility of accessing
لدينا على الأقل أحتمالية الوصول
what makes us feel human, connected.
لما يجعلنا نشعر كبشر, متواصلين
Imagine the ripples of this notion
تخيل تموجات هذه الفكرة
for the millions of people living and dying with dementia.
لملايين من الناس ممن يعيشون ويموتوا بالخرف
Primal sensorial delights that say the things we don't have words for,
المسرات الحسية الأولية التي تقول الاشياء التي لانجد الكلمات لها
impulses that make us stay present --
الدوافع التي تجعلنا حاضرين
no need for a past or a future.
لاحاجة لماضي أو لمستقبل
So, if teasing unnecessary suffering out of the system was our first design cue,
لذا, لو أن أستخراج الألم الغير ضروري من النظام كان بسبب أول إشارة للتصميم
then tending to dignity by way of the senses,
لذا فأن ميلاننا للكرامة بسبب حواسنا,
by way of the body -- the aesthetic realm --
عن طريق الجسد -العالم الجمالي-
is design cue number two.
هو إشارة التصميم الثانية
Now this gets us quickly to the third and final bit for today;
الآن هذا يوصل بنا إلى ثالث وأخر جزء لهذا اليوم
namely, we need to lift our sights, to set our sights on well-being,
أعني, نحن بحاجة أن نرفع أنظارنا, أن نضع نصب أعيننا الرخاء
so that life and health and healthcare
حتى أن الحياة والصحة والرعاية الصحية
can become about making life more wonderful,
تصبح حول جعل الحياة أكثر روعة
rather than just less horrible.
أكثر من مجرد جعلها أقل فظاعة
Beneficence.
إحسان
Here, this gets right at the distinction
هنا, نجد الفارق
between a disease-centered and a patient- or human-centered model of care,
بين نموذج الرعاية الذي محوره المرض أو محوره البشر
and here is where caring becomes a creative, generative,
وهنا حيث يصبح الأهتمام فعل ابداعي وتوليدي
even playful act.
وإيضا ًمرح
"Play" may sound like a funny word here.
"المرح" لربما تبدو ككلمة مضحكة هنا
But it is also one of our highest forms of adaptation.
لكن أنها أيضا وأحدة من أهم أشكال التكيف
Consider every major compulsory effort it takes to be human.
انظر إلى كل جهد إلزامي نفعله حتى نكون بشر
The need for food has birthed cuisine.
الحاجة للطعام كانت سبب نشأة المطبخ
The need for shelter has given rise to architecture.
الحاجة الى الملجىء جعلتنا نعلي العمران
The need for cover, fashion.
الحاجة للغطاء, الموضة.
And for being subjected to the clock,
وتعرضنا للساعة
well, we invented music.
حسناً, أخترعنا الموسيقى
So, since dying is a necessary part of life,
لذا , بما أن الموت جزء مهم في الحياة,
what might we create with this fact?
ماذا نستطيع أن نخلق مع هذه الحقيقة؟
By "play" I am in no way suggesting we take a light approach to dying
عن طريق " المرح" أنا لا أقترح ابداً أن تأخذ الطريقة الألطف للموت
or that we mandate any particular way of dying.
أو أننا نفوض أي طريقة للموت.
There are mountains of sorrow that cannot move,
هنالك جبال من الحزن لن تتحرك,
and one way or another, we will all kneel there.
وبطريقة أو بأخرى, سنركع جميعا هناك.
Rather, I am asking that we make space --
بدلاً من ذلك , أنا أطلب أن نصنع مساحة
physical, psychic room, to allow life to play itself all the way out --
غرفة جسدية نفسية حتى تسمح للحياة أن تمضي
so that rather than just getting out of the way,
لذا بدلاً من أن يكون الأمر فقط أن تبتعد عن الطريق
aging and dying can become a process of crescendo through to the end.
التقدم بالعمر والموت يصبح عملية تصعيد حتى النهاية
We can't solve for death.
لانستطيع حل الموت.
I know some of you are working on this.
أعلم أن بعضكم يعمل على هذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Meanwhile, we can --
في هذه الاثناء, نستطيع
We can design towards it.
نستطيع أن نخطط تجاهه.
Parts of me died early on,
أجزاء مني قد ماتت بالبداية
and that's something we can all say one way or another.
لكن هنا شيء نستطيع قوله بشكل أو بآخر
I got to redesign my life around this fact,
لقد أعدت التخطيط لحياتي حول هذه الحقيقة
and I tell you it has been a liberation
و أخبركم أنه كان عتق لي
to realize you can always find a shock of beauty or meaning
أن تعي بأنك تستطيع أن تجد صدمة الجمال أو المعنى
in what life you have left,
في الحياة التي تركت
like that snowball lasting for a perfect moment,
ككرة الثلج تلك التى دامت للحظة مثالية
all the while melting away.
إلى أن ذابت
If we love such moments ferociously,
لو نحب مثل هذه اللحظات , بضراوة
then maybe we can learn to live well --
لربما نستطيع أن نعيش بشكل جيد
not in spite of death,
ليس حقداً على الموت
but because of it.
ولكن بسببه
Let death be what takes us,
دع الموت يأخذنا
not lack of imagination.
وليس أفتقار الخيال
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)